{
  "subject": "Commerce",
  "exam": "JAMB",
  "totalQuestions": 21,
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "Commerce is defined as the study of how",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "man utilizes the resources in his physical environment",
        "B": "man produces, distributes and consumes his goods and services",
        "C": "man buys, sells and distributes goods and services",
        "D": "raw materials are changed into finished goods"
      },
      "answer": "C"
    },
    {
      "question": "The type of activity which turns processed raw materials into consumer and industrial goods is described as",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "extractive",
        "B": "manufacturing",
        "C": "constructive",
        "D": "processing"
      },
      "answer": "B"
    },
    {
      "question": "The production process that combines two or more raw materials into one end product is",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "conditioning",
        "B": "blending",
        "C": "merging",
        "D": "synthesis"
      },
      "answer": "D"
    },
    {
      "question": "A demonstration of social responsibility by a business is the payment of",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "taxes to government",
        "B": "dividends to shareholders",
        "C": "interest on loans",
        "D": "premium for insurance"
      },
      "answer": "A"
    },
    {
      "question": "A distinguishing characteristic of a limited liability company is that it",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "is a collection of many sole proprietors",
        "B": "is a multiple partnership",
        "C": "can sue and be sued",
        "D": "has limited resources"
      },
      "answer": "C"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following takes place when firms producing at different stages in the same industry combine?",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "Conglomeration",
        "B": "Vertical integration",
        "C": "Horizontal integration",
        "D": "Cartel"
      },
      "answer": "B"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following groups is paid first when a firm liquidates?",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "Preference shareholders",
        "B": "Debenture holders",
        "C": "Ordinary shareholders",
        "D": "Cumulative preference shareholders"
      },
      "answer": "B"
    },
    {
      "question": "Compulsory dissolution of a business can arise from",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "an agreement by the owners",
        "B": "a declaration by a court of law",
        "C": "the termination of its life",
        "D": "an unfavourable economic climate"
      },
      "answer": "B"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the working capital as at December 31, 1992?",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "N65,250",
        "B": "N60,000",
        "C": "N48,650",
        "D": "N41,950"
      },
      "answer": "C"
    },
    {
      "question": "A company earned a total revenue of N108 million with a total cost of N91 million in 1991. If it paid 45% tax on its gross profit for that year, determine its net profit.",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "N24.65 million",
        "B": "N17.00 million",
        "C": "N9.35 million",
        "D": "N7.65 million"
      },
      "answer": "B"
    },
    {
      "question": "What are fixtures and fittings in a balance sheet?",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "Liquid capital",
        "B": "Current assets",
        "C": "Fixed assets",
        "D": "Working capital"
      },
      "answer": "C"
    },
    {
      "question": "Government impose import duties for the following reasons EXCEPT",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "to raise revenue for other services",
        "B": "to act as a retaliatory measure against other governments",
        "C": "to discourage the redistribution of income at home",
        "D": "to protect home industries from external competition"
      },
      "answer": "C"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sole enterprise may flourish best in",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "a mining business",
        "B": "a retailing business",
        "C": "an oil exploration business",
        "D": "a car assembly business"
      },
      "answer": "B"
    },
    {
      "question": "The use of coin-operated machines to sell goods is a form of",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "personal selling",
        "B": "retailing",
        "C": "wholesaling",
        "D": "mail-order selling"
      },
      "answer": "B"
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the major function of the wholesaler?",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "Buying from small-scale producers and selling to exporters",
        "B": "Buying in bulk and selling in small quantities",
        "C": "Granting of credit facilities to retailers",
        "D": "Providing information to manufacturers on market situation"
      },
      "answer": "B"
    },
    {
      "question": "The rate at which a countryâ€™s exports exchange for its imports is called",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "balance of payments",
        "B": "balance of trade",
        "C": "terms of payment",
        "D": "terms of trade"
      },
      "answer": "D"
    },
    {
      "question": "The difference between the total payments for imports and the receipts from exports within a given period is referred to as",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "balance of payments",
        "B": "balance of trade",
        "C": "comparative cost advantage",
        "D": "comparative advantage"
      },
      "answer": "A"
    },
    {
      "question": "A pro forma invoice is NOT required when",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "quoting for the supply of goods",
        "B": "goods are sent on approval",
        "C": "dealing regularly with a customer",
        "D": "final prices are uncertain"
      },
      "answer": "C"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following statements is TRUE about sea transport?",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "All ships have specific routes to ply",
        "B": "All ships must be insured at every journey",
        "C": "All ships are insured separately from the crew",
        "D": "All ships normally arrive at their destination with goods"
      },
      "answer": "D"
    },
    {
      "question": "The postal organization which preceded the Nigerian Postal Service is",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "Post and Telecommunications",
        "B": "Post and Telephone",
        "C": "Post and Teleprinter",
        "D": "Post and Telegraph"
      },
      "answer": "A"
    },
    {
      "question": "Goods discharged from ships on which import duties have not been paid are kept in the",
      "hasImage": false,
      "options": {
        "A": "ordinary warehouse",
        "B": "public warehouse",
        "C": "private warehouse",
        "D": "bonded warehouse"
      },
      "answer": "D"
    }
  ]
}